Good morning, today's דף Daf is ח Ches and we pick up
on five lines from the top. רבי אלעזר ורבי שמעון אומרים באחד
בתשרי. Rabbi Elazar veRabbi Shimon omrim be'echad beTishrei. So we finally have
moved on from אחד בניסן echad beNissan
and unpacking the different ways in which אחד בניסן echad beNissan was
ראש חודש, Rosh Chodesh, particularly with a look at בל תאחר, Bal
Te'acher, an extensive look at בל תאחר, Bal Te'acher, then a ברייתא
Baraisa that had a number of other ways in
which ניסן Nissan was ראש השנה, Rosh Hashanah, and now we move
on to the other ראשי שנה Roshei Shanah and the issue about
מעשר בהמה. Ma'aser Behema. So we have that the idea of the
תנא קמא, Tanna Kamma, which is that אלול Elul is the ראש
השנה Rosh Hashanah for מעשר בהמה, Ma'aser Behema, and now the debate.
רבי אלעזר ורבי שמעון אומרים באחד בתשרי. Rabbi Elazar veRabbi Shimon omrim
be'echad beTishrei. So רבי אלעזר ורבי שמעון Rabbi Elazar veRabbi Shimon say
it is on the first of תשרי. Tishrei. So let's take a
look. אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar Rabbi Yochanan, says רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan,
ושניהם מקרא אחד דרשו, v'shneihem mikra echad darshu, they both learned it
out from the same verse. What is the verse? לבושו כרים הצאן
ועמקים יעטפו בר יתרועעו אף ישירו. Levushu charim hatzon ve'amakim ya'atfu bar
yitro'u af yashiru.
So
the blankets will cloak the sheep, but this is understood to mean
that the male sheep will mount the female sheep, they'll be covered
up, you know, so I mean one sheep will cover up the
other in this act, you know, in having sex. ועמקים יעטפו בר,
ve'amakim ya'atfu bar, the valleys will be, you know, sort of cloaked
in grain. יתרועעו אף ישירו, yitro'u af yashiru, they will like bleat
forth or trumpet forth, even give song. So what does that have
to do with anything? So let's take a look. So says רבי
מאיר סבר, Rabbi Meir savar, רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir holds that the
ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah for the מעשר בהמה, Ma'aser Behema, which means
when the year of the sheep ends, sounds like Chinese, the year
of the sheep, anyway, is
so he said רבי מאיר סבר, Rabbi Meir savar, אימתי לבושו כרים
הצאן, eimatai levushu charim hatzon, when is it that the sheep are
mounting, you know, that
they're reproducing, not reproducing, but that they're being, you know, they're basically
what's the word,
not conceived, conceiving, this mating happens בזמן שעמקים יעטפו בר, bizman she'amakim
ya'atfu bar, that happens at the time when the valleys are cloaked
in grain. Now ואימתי עמקים יעטפו בר, ve'eimatai amakim ya'atfu bar, when
are the valleys cloaked in grain? באדר, beAdar, okay? It is in
אדר. Adar. So it is ניסן Nissan is like when the grain
becomes ripe and the barley becomes ready to be harvested, but the
original cloaking of the grain already happens in אדר. Adar. So the
sheep are therefore mating in אדר. Adar. So מתעברות באדר,
mit'abrot beAdar, they conceive in אדר, Adar, ויולדות באב, ve'yoldot beAv, and
they give birth in אב Av because apparently sheep give birth after
five months of gestation. ניסן, אייר, סיון, תמוז, אב, Nissan, Iyar, Sivan,
Tammuz, Av, okay? So therefore they give birth in אב. Av. So
if they're giving birth in אב, Av, that's the new year's crop
of sheep get born in אב. Av. So the ראש השנה, Rosh
Hashanah, the end of that year, you know, defines the end of
one and the beginning of the next is after the new crop
has been born. ראש השנה שלהם אלול, Rosh Hashanah shelahem Elul, so
the ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah is the first of אלול. Elul. Yes,
so what's your question? How come we're looking? Yes, okay, I saw
you raised your hand. No, okay, fine. So ראש השנה שלהם אלול.
Rosh Hashanah shelahem Elul. רבי אלעזר ורבי שמעון אומרים, Rabbi Elazar veRabbi
Shimon omrim, רבי אלעזר ורבי שמעון Rabbi Elazar and Rabbi Shimon say,
אימתי לבושו כרים הצאן, eimatai levushu charim hatzon, no, when is it
that the mates are being, the sheep are being cloaked with quote-unquote
blankets, that they're mating?
בזמן שיתרועעו אף ישירו. bizman sheyitro'u af yashiru. It skips over the
ועמקים יעטפו בר ve'amakim ya'atfu bar and goes to יתרועעו אף ישירו,
yitro'u af yashiru, when they are trumpeting forth and giving song. אימתי
שבולים אומרות שירה, eimatai shivalin omrot shira, when is it that the
stalks are giving song? Meaning like the wind blows through the stalks
and they make a rustling and that's the giving forth of song
that this is referring to. The valleys that are cloaked in grain
are giving forth song because the grain is like rustling in the
wind. But when does that happen? That's בניסן, beNissan, that's not באדר,
beAdar, you know, they have to grow a little bit higher and
get a little riper before this reality exists. So that's it's only
happening in ניסן Nissan and they're mating. מתעברות
בניסן, mit'abrot beNissan, so they become pregnant in ניסן, Nissan, ויולדות באלול,
ve'yoldot be'Elul, they give birth in אלול, Elul, a month later. So
if they're giving birth in אלול, Elul, ראש השנה שלהם תשרי, Rosh
Hashanah shelahem Tishrei, their ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah is תשרי. Tishrei. So
basically the question, although so fascinating that it's learning it from a
verse, the question is when are sheep mating, when do primarily do
sheep give birth, and therefore after the basic period where sheep are
primarily giving birth, then you are going to have the ראש השנה
Rosh Hashanah to be the month that follows that, that's the new
year. Now of course, one would imagine that both of these things
are happening, which is what the גמרא Gemara is going to say,
that there are sheep being born
in, in אלול, Elul, in אלול. Elul. Or else, you know what,
they're just looking at a פסוק? Pasuk? I mean, there must be
a reality out there. And that's what the גמרא Gemara will say,
that actually it is happening in both in אב Av and in
אלול. Elul. The question is which one do you put your emphasis
on? Okay, so let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara.
Oh, sorry, you don't
see these פסוקים Psukim
as אסמכתא?
Asmachta? Yeah, yeah.
I mean, I was basically going to ask, if this was biblical,
it would be, it should be in חומש, Chumash, not from תהלים.
Tehillim.
Well, okay, that's not always such a question. You know, you could
use תהלים Tehillim to do גילוי מילתא gilluy milta בעלמא, be'alma, it's
not really telling you הלכה, Halacha, it's just clueing you into the
facts and so on. But anyways, let's take a look at the
גמרא, Gemara, okay, how much are you really going to get from
the פסוקים. Psukim. So גמרא Gemara does seem to treat it seriously.
Let's take a look. So גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay, Rosh
Hashanah 7b, ואידך נמי הכתיב יתרועעו אף ישירו. ve'idach nami hachtiv yitroa'u
af yashiru. The one that says that you go, that the mating
occurs in אדר Adar and not in ניסן, Nissan, doesn't it also
speak about them bursting forth in trumpeting and in song, which happens
later in ניסן? Nissan? ההוא באפלי. hahu be'aflei.
No, that's like the ones that are late. The late maters do
it in ניסן. Nissan. דהני בניסן. dehani beNissan.
But the primary mating happens in אדר Adar and the primary birthing
happens in אב. Av. ואידך נמי הכתיב עמקים יעטפו בר. ve'idach nami
hachtiv amakim ya'atfu var.
But the other one, doesn't it say that the valleys will be
cloaked in grain? So, which happens in אדר. Adar. Doesn't it say
that's also when the mating happens? ההוא בחריפתא. hahu becharifta.
No, that's the ones that are mating early. דאקדמו מאדר. de'akdimu meAdar.
But they start in אדר. Adar. Which means both things happen. There's
mating in אדר, Adar, there's ניסן. Nissan. Or there's mating,
there's birthing in אב, Av, there's birthing in אלול. Elul. The question
is which one do you say is the primary? And which one
do you say, yeah, that's the early one or that's the late
one, but the real one is this one. Right? So it's looking
at the reality where both things are happening, where they're giving birth
throughout the whole period, and identifying which is the one that I
see to be the primary and which one am I going to
sort of say is secondary? But they both agree that the מציאות
Metzius is both things happen. Now I have to tell you that
if they both agree that the מציאות Metzius is that both things
happen, it really does not, personally I don't understand how you would
put a ראש השנה, Rosh Hashanah, you know, after the primary crop
is born, before the late ones are born. You know, but it's
still all the ending of the birthing from the previous year. You
want the ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah to be after the whole process
is over. Not just after the primary part is over. So even
if you admit that the primary thing is being born in אב,
Av, and, yeah, אב, Av, and the secondarily, the, you know, the
late ones are being born in אלול, Elul, you would still say
fine, make the ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah after everything is born, make
the ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah in תשרי. Tishrei. So I don't really
understand, you know, the logic here that it all goes by what's
primary rather than going when the whole thing is over, which should
have everybody agreeing תשרי. Tishrei. Anyways, that's my הערה. He'arah. Let's see
where the גמרא Gemara goes with it. Yes, Charlie.
Oh, שטיינזלץ Steinsaltz says that actually most sheep conceive in the fall
and give birth in the spring.
So much for all of this. So
I have no confidence in this at any attempt to reconcile this.
Not really.
Okay then. Excellent.
But now the גמרא Gemara goes out.
Babylonian sheep.
Exactly.
Or Israel sheep. I mean, does it say, does it say where
it's looking at, it's just sheep in general. All right. So the
גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay. בשלמא לרבי מאיר כדכתיב. bishlama leRabbi
Meir kidechtiv. So according to רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, the verse reads
well. לבשו כרים הצאן, lavshu charim hatzon, when do they mate? בזמן
שעמקים יעטפו בר, bizman she'amakim ya'atfu var, when the valleys are cloaked
in grain, in אדר. Adar. וגדי נמי, ve'gadi nami, and after that
happens, there's also a next crop of יתרועעו אף ישירו, yitroa'u af
yashiru, that do it when the, when the, you know, the wheat
is rustling, when the grain is rustling and they're giving forth song.
That's a later crop that happens in ניסן. Nissan. אלא לרבי אלעזר
ורבי שמעון. ela leRabbi Elazar veRabbi Shimon. But according to רבי אלעזר
Rabbi Elazar and רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, that they focus the primary
thing on ניסן Nissan and just the early thing on אדר, Adar,
איפכא מיבעי ליה, ipcha mibei leh, the פסוק Pasuk should be written
in the opposite order. Right? The פסוק Pasuk is strange. לבשו כרים
הצאן בזמן שיתרועעו אף ישירו. lavshu charim hatzon bizman sheyitroa'u af yashiru.
It should have started by saying that the mating happens when the
grain is rustling in ניסן. Nissan. וגדי נמי, ve'gadi nami, and secondarily,
there's also early ones, ועמקים יעטפו בר, ve'amakim ya'atfu var, that happen
when the thing is originally, when the valleys are originally cloaked in
grain. So, the פסוק Pasuk is a funny read according to them
because it's giving primacy to the thing that they are saying is
the secondary
period. אלא אמר רבא, ela amar Rava, דכולי עלמא, dechulei alma, לבשו
כרים הצאן בזמן שעמקים יעטפו בר. lavshu charim hatzon bizman she'amakim ya'atfu
var. Everybody agrees that the basic mating period occurs like the פסוק
Pasuk says, when the valley is cloaked in grain, which means in
אדר. Adar. And it's the basic period. It occurs in Adar, then
everybody agrees that the basic birthing period occurs in אב *Av*. So
what's the issue whether it's אלול Elul *Elul* or תשרי Tishrei *Tishrei*?
So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, הכא בהאי קרא קמיפלגי *hacha be-hai kra
kamipeligi*, and here's what they're debating on. עשר תעשר *Aser te'aser*, you
shall take your tithes, את כל תבואת זרעך *et kol tevuat zarecha*,
בשני מעשרות הכתוב מדבר *bi-shnei ma'asrot ha-katuv medaber*, אחד מעשר בהמה ואחד
מעשר דגן *echad ma'aser behemah ve-echad ma'aser dagan*. So because it says
you shall take your tithes in this double language, עשר תעשר *aser
te'aser*, we say it's talking, it's alluding not only to the tithing
of grain but also to the tithing of animals and linking the
two. So for what purpose is it linking the two? רבי מאיר
סבר *Rabbi Meir savar*, מקיש מעשר בהמה למעשר דגן *makish ma'aser behemah
le-ma'aser dagan*. Here's the reason the Torah compares the two. Why? מה
מעשר דגן סמוך לגמרו עישורו *mah ma'aser dagan samuch le-gemaro isuro*. The
same way by grain, when it is near being completed,
or I should say it that way, soon after the period of
its completion is when you take ma'aser. What determines, when is the
new year for grain? We're going to learn in the next clause
of the משנה Mishnah *mishnah*, תשרי Tishrei *Tishrei*. Why- why Tishrei? What
happens- what happens right around Tishrei? What חג chag *chag* is in
Tishrei? Right, it's סוכות Succos *Sukkot*. What's סוכות Succos *Sukkot*? Right, חג
Chag... האסיף *Chag Ha-asif*. You're gathering in the grain. So the ending
of the process of the grain determines when the new year is
for ma'aser. The ma'aser year begins when the end process, when the
process ended. Although it is interesting, right, because talking about making a
new year in the middle of a process, which is what I
was talking about before the sheep, if סוכות *Sukkot* is when you're
doing the gathering in, so then the new year is starting before
the processing is fully complete, right, which is a little bit bizarre.
So anyway, but nevertheless, by the grain we see that the new
year for ma'aser is- is right after or juxtaposed to the ending
of the previous, of the sort of, of the finishing of the
process of the grain. סמוך לגמרו עישורו *Samuch le-gemaro isuro*, אף מעשר
בהמה סמוך לגמרו עישורו *af ma'aser behemah samuch le-gemaro isuro*. So similarly
by animals, right juxtaposed to right after it's done, meaning if the
birthing is primarily happening in אב *Av*, so right after that period
of it being done, of it being born, that's when you have
the ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah *Rosh Hashanah* in אלול Elul *Elul* right
afterwards, just like, so it's paralleling in terms of the logic behind
it. רבי אלעזר ורבי שמעון סברי *Rabbi Elazar ve-Rabbi Shimon savri*, but
Rabbi Elazar and Rabbi Shimon say no, מקיש מעשר בהמה למעשר דגן
*makish ma'aser behemah le-ma'aser dagan*. Here's the way they're linked, not in
terms of identifying a similar application of the same underlying reasoning, but
just completely looking at the form. And they say מה מעשר דגן
ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah שלו תשרי Tishrei. *mah ma'aser dagan Rosh Hashanah
shelo Tishrei*, אף מעשר בהמה ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah שלו תשרי Tishrei
*af ma'aser behemah Rosh Hashanah shelo Tishrei*. No, it's a simple link,
תשרי-תשרי *Tishrei-Tishrei*. So one says yes, they're linked. How are they linked?
The same date or the same logic? And if you say same
date, it's תשרי Tishrei *Tishrei*. If you say same logic, it's going
to be אלול *Elul*. So that's what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says,
although again it was I think a little bit more interesting putting
the פסוק pasuk *pasuk* aside when it was actually acknowledging that this
process happens over time like the period of חג Chag האסיף *Chag
Ha-asif*, and then do you sort of put the ראש השנה Rosh
Hashanah, *Rosh Hashanah* after the primary period is over or after the
whole period is over? Okay, yes.
In general that's a really interesting question in cultures. In other words,
where do you mark a process? Like when should יום Yom השואה
*Yom Ha-shoah* be, right? It's a process of human experience but you
need to mark it with a memory. So it's part of this
whole thing. Nice point.
Nice point. Okay.
Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* goes on, let's take a
look. So now באחד בתשרי ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah. לשנים lashanim *be-echad
be-Tishrei Rosh Hashanah le-shanim*. So we've done now two. We've done ניסן
Nisan *Nisan* and אלול *Elul*, although אלול *Elul* is debated, but we
have this possibility of that second one of מעשר בהמה *ma'aser behemah*.
And now we get to תשרי Tishrei. *Tishrei*, and תשרי Tishrei. *Tishrei*
has a whole list of things. To remind you what the list
of things are about תשרי Tishrei. *Tishrei* in the first משנה mishna
*mishnah*, it says ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah לשנים *Rosh Hashanah le-shanim* for
years, whatever that means. ולשמיטין *Ve-li-shmitin*, it starts the new שמיטה Shemitah.
*shmitah* year, begins on, the cycle of, if there's a שמיטה Shemitah
*shmitah*, what year it is in the cycle of the seven year
cycle begins on תשרי Tishrei *Tishrei*, like which מעשר *ma'aser* year it
is, whether it's a שמיטה Shemitah, *shmitah* year, יובלות yovlot *yovelot*, יובל
Yovel. *yovel* begins on תשרי Tishrei. *Tishrei*, נטיעה וירקות *neti'ah ve-yerakot*. נטיעה
*Neti'ah* is planting for ערלה *orlah*, which year of ערלה *orlah* it
is gets incremented not from the date the tree was planted.
You don't wait till the birthday of the tree, it gets incremented
at ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah? *Rosh Hashanah* on תשרי Tishrei. *Tishrei*, and
ירקות *yerakot* is מעשר ירק *ma'aser yerek*, when the vegetables are harvested
you go by, which מעשר *ma'aser* year it goes by, it goes
for them by תשרי Tishrei. *Tishrei*. Okay, so all these things, a
lot about the agricultural
מצוות mitzvot, *mitzvot* of תרומות ומעשרות *terumot u-ma'asrot* and שמיטה Shemitah *shmitah*
and יובל Yovel *yovel*, all of those things plus a few others.
So now let's take a look though what the first line means,
לשנים *le-shanim*, for years. What does that mean for years? למאי הלכתא
*Le-mai hilchata*? For what purpose are you telling me that תשרי Tishrei,
*Tishrei* is the beginning of the year? אמר רב פפא *Amar Rav
Pappa*, לשטרות lishtaros *le-shtarot*, for documents. דתנן *De-tenan*, שטרי חוב המוקדמין פסולים
המאוחרים כשרים *shitrei chov ha-mukdamin pesulim ha-me'ucharim kesherim*. This might sound familiar.
If it's predated it's invalid, post-dated it's valid, so you have to
make sure you're writing the right date on the document, so you
have to know whether to increment it. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
says, when does the year get incremented? So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
says, ורמינהו דתנן *ve-reminhu de-tenan* באחד בניסן *be-echad be-Nisan*. באחד בניסן ראש
השנה Rosh Hashanah. למלכים. One minute, but the first line in the
משנה mishna is the first of ניסן Nisan is ראש השנה Rosh
Hashanah for kings. דאמינא למאי הלכתא, d'amina l'mai hilchasa, what's the halakhic
relevance of calling it a new year for kings? ואמר רב חסדא
v'amar Rav Chisda לשטרות for documents. So make up your mind. Do
you go by ניסן Nisan or תשרי Tishrei when you're incrementing the
years on your documents? So the גמרא Gemara. says לא קשיא, lo
kashya, not difficult. כאן במלכי ישראל כאן במלכי אומות העולם, kan b'malchei
Yisrael, kan b'malchei umos ha'olam, which is the difference whether it is
the Jewish kings or the non-Jewish kings. The Jewish kings you'll increment
at ניסן Nisan because that also focuses החודש הזה לכם ראש חודשים,
hachodesh hazeh lachem rosh chodashim, and the emphasis of פסח Pesach and
ניסן Nisan, being the beginning of the year and the beginning of
the counting of the months. For non-Jewish kings you would go for
the first of תשרי Tishrei. and therefore depending on whether you are
dating your document to Jewish kings or non-Jewish kings, the years will
increment
differently.
Does that mean if I'm doing business with a Jew I date
the deed one way and if I'm doing business with a gentile
I date it differently?
It could be. It could be. The גמרא Gemara also says that
certain documents they said are supposed to be for the gentile kings
because of שלום מלכות. shalom malchus. You want to be. So but
yeah. Exactly when you do one, there are different
circumstances. And also it's not just it's the same year but you're,
when I do with a non-Jew I call it 2013 and when
I do with a Jew I call it 2014. It's for different
kings. So according to one I'm saying in the seventh year of
King David's reign and in the other I'm saying in the 24th
year of so-and-so's reign. So if you're referencing a different king, and
when you're doing a Jewish king it goes by ניסן, Nisan non-Jewish
it goes by תשרי. Tishrei. Now interestingly,
I always understood that the חידוש chiddush of the תורה, Torah, and
this might still be true, but החודש הזה לכם ראש חודשים hachodesh
hazeh lachem rosh chodashim is that because the natural agricultural cycle has
תשרי Tishrei at the beginning, which is why we have תשרי Tishrei
for us for counting. It's funny that the גמרא Gemara by the
way does not mention, if I told you the number of the
year increments on ראש חודש תשרי, Rosh Chodesh Tishrei, what number of
the year would you say gets incremented? What number for us increments
on ראש חודש תשרי? Rosh Chodesh Tishrei?
The בריאת העולם, brias ha'olam, right? The counting not to a king,
right, but for creation. 5774, right, not 2013, 2014, right? Where we
increment from creation. It's interesting that the גמרא Gemara, does not reference
that as a way of documenting שטרות. shtaros. Okay, but normally anyway
we, the year presumably, the natural way I've always assumed, is to
start at תשרי. Tishrei. We'll see later the גמרא Gemara בתשרי נברא
העולם b'Tishrei nivra ha'olam and so on. That's when we assumed that
the world was created. We'll get to that in a minute. But
more than just the issue of counting from creation is the fact
that the agricultural cycle naturally is a תשרי. Tishrei, So it's like
the school year begins in September, right? So why does the school
year begin in September? Why don't our schools because the kids would
go home and help their parents on the farm,
and then whatever the new agricultural cycle would begin would begin in
September. That's when the plowing and the planting and all of that
begins, right? And that's why what do you call it? סוכות is
בצאת השנה b'tzeis hashanah or בתקופת השנה b'tkufas hashanah because by סוכות
is when you're ending one period and you're gathering in the grain
from one and you're beginning the next period. So the agricultural cycle
naturally is a תשרי. Tishrei. And then the תורה Torah comes along
and says no, now it's not just about the natural world. There's
about history and God and החודש הזה לכם ראש חודשים. hachodesh hazeh
lachem rosh chodashim. There's a different way of counting. There's a way
of counting from redemption and from God's intervention in
history. And that creates its own type of a cycle and a
way of perceiving of time, not just in terms of the natural
world. And that's the חידוש chiddush of that the months start from
ניסן Nisan and ראש חודשים Rosh Chodashim although the years in the
end are still incrementing from תשרי Tishrei, in terms of בריאת העולם.
brias ha'olam. It explains why you have that bizarre thing that the
months are numbered from ניסן Nisan, and the years are numbered from
תשרי. Tishrei There are essentially two different cycles going on here: the
natural agricultural and the historical Jewish revelation. So that explains this difference
also again about the Jewish kings ניסן, Nisan, non-Jewish kings תשרי. Tishrei
The only thing that a little throws a wrench in it is
that and I'd have to look into this more, but somebody told
me that in
בבל, Bavel, because they got these also names of the months from
Babylon, that actually the year did start in ניסן, Nisan not in
תשרי. Tishrei So it wasn't only sort of a- apparently, because that's
another logical way to start the year. Spring is the time where
things are coming alive. There's like the dead of winter and then
they and right, well it's also redemptive in terms of גאולה geulah
and history but even if look at the natural world. When would
you say the year begins? Planting begins in in תשרי, Tishrei. in
the fall, but the birthing maybe begins in the
spring. So apparently that's also another sort of way in which in
a natural sense ניסן Nisan, could be seen as the beginning of
the year as well.
But why do we date כתובות kesuvos to both תשרי Tishrei and
בריאת העולם? brias ha'olam?
Yeah, so that's a good question. Let's hold off on that a
bit because again in the it used to be that there was
this thing called מניין שטרות minyan shtaros as well. So let's move
on a bit in the גמרא. Gemara So the גמרא Gemara says
like this. Okay, so anyway, it depends how you're... counting Jewish kings
ניסן, Nisan non-Jewish kings תשרי. Tishrei So the גמרא Gemara. says רב
חסדא. Rav Chisda. So the גמרא, Gemara רב חסדא, Rav Chisda, מתניתין
אשלאן אשנין. Masnitin ashlan ashnyan. So one minute. So if רב חסדא
Rav Chisda says the difference between מלכי ישראל Malchei Yisrael and מלכי
אומות העולם, Malchei Umot HaOlam, right, and that's when the משנה mishna
says ניסן Nisan, it's only talking about
מלכי ישראל, Malchei Yisrael, so it sounds like he's saying his whole
חידוש. chiddush. Ah, I'm going to tell you something. The משנה mishna.
says ניסן, Nisan. but that's only for מלכי ישראל, Malchei Yisrael, you
know, מלכי אומות העולם Malchei Umot HaOlam is תשרי. Tishrei, But now
you're telling me that the משנה mishna says תשרי Tishrei is years
as well. So it's just פשט pshat in the משנה. mishna. When
the משנה mishna says תשרי Tishrei is years, it means non-Jewish kings,
years go from תשרי. Tishrei? So why is רב חסדא Rav Chisda
saying a חידוש? chiddush? It's really just פשט pshat in the משנה.
mishna. So you could say he's telling me what the משנה mishna
means. But okay. גמרא Gemara says לא רב חסדא קרא אתא לאשמועינן.
Lo Rav Chisda kra ata le'ashmian. רב חסדא Rav Chisda is coming
to explain to us פסוקים, psukim, meaning that there are פסוקים, psukim,
you know, about, if you remember the גמרא Gemara quoted the פסוקים
psukim about how we know that you increment the years, and it
quoted some פסוקים psukim from נחמיה, Nechemya, remember by the Persian kings?
And there it was תשרי, Tishrei and by the Jewish kings שלמה
Shlomo was ניסן. Nisan. So רב חסדא Rav Chisda was not coming
to explain the משנה. mishna The משנה mishna does in a way
reflect those two countings. רב חסדא Rav Chisda was coming to reconcile
the verses. Okay, so what have we said now? Version number one
is that the משנה mishna when it says מלכים Melachim means counting
for non-Jewish kings and for Jewish kings and that's ניסן. Nisan And
when it says שנים, shanim, it means counting for non-Jewish kings and
that's from תשרי. Tishrei? Okay, ואיבעית אימא, Ve'iba'it eima, if you want
I'll tell you, רב חסדא כרבי זירא מתני לה. Rav Chisda k'Rebbi
Zeira matni lah. You know what, you're right. רב חסדא Rav Chisda
is saying his חידוש chiddush and he's saying his חידוש chiddush in
the משנה mishna and he's making a distinction between ניסן Nisan and
תשרי, Tishrei? but he's saying it about, you know, Jewish and non-Jewish
kings, but he's saying that as his own חידוש. chiddush. It's not
פשט, pshat, it's not what the second phrase in the משנה Mishnah
means. So what does the second phrase in the משנה Mishnah. mean
when it says תשרי Tishrei is the beginning of years? It means
something else. It means what רבי זירא Rebbi Zeira says. What does
רבי זירא Rebbi Zeira say? רבי זירא אמר לתקופה. Rebbi Zeira amar
litkufa. רבי זירא Rebbi Zeira says
the purpose of saying תשרי Tishrei is the beginning of years is
for תקופה, tkufa, which means what? It means for the astronomical cycle.
For identifying, for sort of counting, how do we, you know, when
we figure out the astronomy, like you know when they sort of
figure out like when you say ברכת החמה, Birkat HaChama, when the
sun is back to where it was, its position... well, yeah, but
here also, right, the positioning of the sun relative to the constellations,
right, and where was that when the world was created? So, well,
when was the world created? So he's basically saying that he believes
that this goes back... that תשרי Tishrei is when the world was
created, and therefore when you want to sort of figure out where
are we relative to the original placement of the sun and the
stars and the constellations, so you should know that we are going
to sort of focus on how everything was sort of, you know,
what place everything was on the first of תשרי. Tishrei, Now, it's
really a bit of, you know, glossing over the problem here, which
is what difference does it make? Right? You know where things are
now. You know, if you sort of know the math, you know,
sort of the system in which they work, you sort of retroactively
figure out where they were. So 5,774
years ago in תשרי Tishrei. they were in place X, and 5,774
years ago in ניסן Nisan. they were in place Y. So other
than for the הלכה halakha of ברכת החמה, Birkat HaChama,
who cares? I mean, it's just an arbitrary point in a process
that you're sort of counting from. So there's a long תוספות Tosafot
which I have to tell you I don't really understand because it
gets into all the computation of תקופות, tkufot, which are beyond me,
but he tries to sort of explain why some of this matters
in terms of what you define as your starting point. At least
I'll say the נפקא מינה nafka mina is for ברכת החמה, Birkat
HaChama, which is the one הלכה halakha which is based on where
we think everything was, you know, בשעת בריאת העולם. b'shat briyat ha'olam.
Yes.
But our custom for ברכת החמה Birkat HaChama is actually based on
the new year being in ניסן. Nisan.
Because we say it right before
פסח.
Pesach.
Is that true, that it's based on the position?
It's actually ערב פסח erev Pesach the last time.
Because it's so funny because in all other ways we say that
we basically פוסקין pasken that בתשרי נברא העולם. beTishrei nivra ha'olam.
Yeah, and that's in our פיוטים piyyutim on יום כיפור. Yom Kippur.
But ברכת החמה Birkat HaChama is always in ניסן.
Nisan Wow, I'm going to have to get back to you on
that. That is a good point. Okay. So anyway, רבי אליעזר Rebbi
Eliezer he and this is going according to רבי אליעזר Rebbi Eliezer
דאמר בתשרי נברא העולם. de'amar beTishrei nivra ha'olam. So therefore if you
want to figure out where we are sort of, you know, in
terms of the positioning of the sun and the stars and the
seasons and so on, then he's saying that we sort of look
back to the first of תשרי Tishrei? is the beginning of a
new astronomical year.
Yes, the גמרא Gemara, in ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah was pointing out
that yes, בתשרי נברא, beTishrei nivra, but the תוספות Tosafot holds...
right, right, right, but Charlie, right, meaning it's certainly possible to hold
תשרי, Tishrei, yes, but Charlie I think but the point still is
that what do you call it is that it is a little
bizarre because in other areas we hold that, you know, we basically
say בתשרי נברא העולם. beTishrei nivra ha'olam. Right, no, but Charlie right.
Charlie is
not asking a קשיא kasha on the גמרא. Gemara He's pointing out
an inconsistency between our... תשרי Tishrei. would be, we do ברכת החמה
Birchas Hachama let’s just say in תשרי Tishrei, on the first day
of תשרי? Tishrei.
No, so that’s another good point also because it’s about, because if
you what when we really say נברא עולם Nivra Olam it’s really
we saying when אדם Adam was created and therefore we actually say
that the world was created like on the twenty-fifth of אלול really
and not on the first. And that’s actually in the beginning of
תוספות, Tosafos, if you take look at this תוספות Tosafos he says
about ten lines down he says like this:
with line that starts with the word תשמואל, Tishmuel, he says סבר
כרבי יהושע דלרבי אליעזר בכ"ה באלול נברא העולם, לרבי יהושע בכ"ה באדר
היינו דכשנברא אדם בשישי קידש החודש. savor k'Rabbi Yehoshua de'le'Rabbi Eliezer be'chaf-hei
be'Elul nivra ha-olam, le'Rabbi Yehoshua be'chaf-hei be'Adar hainu de'kshe'nivra Adam be'shishi kidesh
hachodesh. And then and that’s when it was either ראש חודש תשרי
Rosh Chodesh Tishrei or ראש חודש ניסן. Rosh Chodesh Nissan. Okay,
anyway, but he tries to go through all the astronomical things. Yes
Joel, you wanted to say something? Okay, so now let’s go on.
So he says ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah for תשרי Tishrei. basically means,
now we would say in a simple נפקא מינא nafka mina is
if you’re counting by בריאת העולם, Brias Haolam, that’s when you increment
the שטרות shtaros which goes back to Dov's point, Dovell's point there,
which is that it seems from the גמרא Gemara they’re not referring
to בריאת העולם Brias Haolam as a system of dating שטרות, shtaros,
they’re only referring to the idea of מלכים. melachim. Otherwise that would
have been an easy sort of application of this. Okay, but one
explanation is it’s a way of counting the years for non-Jewish kings.
The other answer is that it is the way of identifying, counting
the years from creation and from, you know, and it’s used for
sort of an astronomical years and for astronomical computations.
רב נחמן בר יצחק אמר לדין. Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak amar ledin.
And now we actually turn to what for us is the significance
of ראש השנה, Rosh Hashanah it is a day of judgment. So
you are judged for the whole year on ראש השנה. Rosh Hashanah's
So it’s the New Year and the way we experience the New
Year, you’re being judged for the following year דכתיב מראשית השנה ועד
אחרית שנה. de'ksiv mereishis hashanah v'ad acharis shanah. God looks at the
land or looks at the people from the beginning of the year
to the end of the year. מראשית השנה נידון מה יהיה בסופה.
mereishis hashanah nidon ma yehei besofah. And from the beginning of the
year God is giving a judgment what will be at the end.
ממאי דתשרי הוא? mimai d'Tishrei hu? And how do you know that’s
from תשרי? Tishrei. On תשרי? Tishrei דכתיב תקעו בחודש שופר בכסא ליום
חגנו כי חק לישראל הוא משפט לאלהי יעקב, de'ksiv tiku bachodesh shofar
bakese l'yom chageinu ki chok l'Yisrael hu mishpat lelohei Yaakov, right?
The פסוק pasuk that’s often interpreted in the context of ראש השנה
Rosh Hashanah and the end of the פסוק pasuk is חק לישראל
משפט לאלהי יעקב. chok l'Yisrael mishpat lelohei Yaakov. And how do you
know that’s going to be תשרי Tishrei and ראש השנה? Rosh Hashanah
Well you could just say תקעו בחודש שופר, tiku bachodesh shofar, you’re
blowing the שופר. shofar. Okay, but the גמרא Gemara underscores it even
more: איזו חג שהחודש מתכסה בו? eizu chag shehachodesh miskaseh bo?
What is the holiday that the month is covered? You don’t see
the moon. The only holiday right בכסא ליום חגנו, bakese l'yom chageinu,
what’s the only חג Chag. in our calendar that the moon is
not really visible or barely visible? It’s only a sliver. הוי אומר
זה ראש השנה. hevei omer zeh Rosh Hashanah. That’s ראש השנה. Rosh
Hashanah It’s funny that it just skips over the תקעו בחודש שופר
tiku hachodesh shofar part. דכתיב de'ksiv
and the next verse says כי חק לישראל הוא משפט לאלהי יעקב.
ki chok l'Yisrael hu mishpat lelohei Yaakov. It is a day of
judgment for God, for the people and that’s why ראש השנה Rosh
Hashanah. is לשנים means we are judged for the following year. By
the way תוספות Tosafos always discusses this idea of חודש מתכסה בו,
chodesh miskaseh bo, an interesting position of one of the בעלי התוספות
Baalei HaTosafos that claimed that what it meant was was that there
was no קרבן korban of מוסף Musaf of ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh
on תשרי Tishrei. because there was only a מוסף Musaf of ראש
השנה Rosh Hashanah not a מוסף Musaf of ראש חודש. Rosh Chodesh.
And then תוספות: Tosafos: you can’t say that! Why? Not because there
was a פסוק pasuk that said he couldn’t say that, but there’s
a תוספתא Tosefta that says that you definitely bring a קרבן מוסף
korban Musaf of ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh on ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah.
as well. So then he gets back: no no no, I didn’t
mean that. What I meant was, of course you bring a קרבן
korban of ראש חודש. Rosh Chodesh. What I meant was was that
the פסוקים pesukim sort of you know sort of hide the fact,
they obfuscate the fact that there is a קרבן korban of ראש
חודש Rosh Chodesh and that we also don’t mention it in our
davenen. That when we do a מוסף Musaf of ראש השנה Rosh
Hashanah. we do not bring out its identity as ראש חודש, Rosh
Chodesh, that ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah... both ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah and
ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh but you know that other identity gets subsumed.
So technically you’re right, there is a מוסף Musaf but it is
not something that we sort of focus on, it gets hidden that
other identity. And we don’t say it in the מוסף Musaf of
שמנה עשרה. Shmoneh Esrei. And then רבינו תם Rabbeinu Tam says: actually
I disagree, we do say it in the מוסף Musaf of שמנה
עשרה. Shmoneh Esrei. And thus why on ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah we
follow רבינו תם. Rabbeinu Tam. I don’t know what the ספרדים Sefardim
do but we follow רבינו תם Rabbeinu Tam and we say we
say מלבד milvad you know מוסף... Musaf... what’s the exact language? עולת
החודש ומנחתה.
olas hachodesh
u'minchasah.
We make explicit reference to the fact that there’s also a קרבן
korban of ראש חודש, Rosh Chodesh, but that line actually was inserted
by רבינו תם. Rabbeinu Tam. And so this
interesting read of חודש מתכסה chodesh miskaseh means its identity as ראש
חודש Rosh Chodesh is subsumed and hidden.
Yes, two short things. First of all the פשט pshat of the
פסוק Pasuk is
ראש חודש. Rosh Chodesh. Right. That is a great point. Yeah.
Also, was there a sense that חג התשרי Chag HaTishrei was a
pilgrimage? I mean, חג... chag
Right, or that ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh was a pilgrimage? I mean,
ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh was a pilgrimage?
Yeah, but חג means a pilgrimage, like in שמואל. Shmuel. In other
words, they
went, מדוע את הולכת אליו היום לא חודש
ולא שבת.
Madua At Holechet Elav Hayom, Lo Chodesh
V'Lo Shabbat. Right. I thought you meant מדוע את הולכת אליו היום
לא חודש ולא שבת. Madua At Holechet Elav Hayom, Lo Chodesh V'Lo
Shabbat. That sort of shows there's a pilgrimage idea around this season,
around ראש חודש. Rosh Chodesh.
Yeah, that is true, I would agree with that. Okay, so now
the גמרא Gemara says like this.
Okay, now we have a little אגדתא. Aggadta. I believe we'll have
plenty of אגדתא Aggadta around ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah as יום הדין,
Yom HaDin, but because we're now introducing that idea, we'll have a
little אגדתא. Aggadta. Yes, David, did you have a question?
I was just thinking of a maybe it's not exactly the same
thing.
When the woman goes when her son dies, you know, and she
goes to the prophet to אלישע... Elisha... and the prophet said why
are you going, it's not ראש חודש. Rosh Chodesh. Right.
Yeah, that's what I just mentioned, the אלישע Elisha thing. Yeah. Yeah,
which indicates an idea that there was a pilgrimage idea around the
חודש. Chodesh. It also indicates there's a pilgrimage idea around שבת, Shabbat,
which is a different issue, right? How could you be... right. So
not... well again, sort of to go into a wise person, not
exactly going to the temple. Anyway, alright, let's take a look.
And the יום also, the very last verse...
right, right, right. מדי חודש בחדשו ומדי שבת בשבתו. Midei Chodesh B'Chodsho
U'Midei Shabbat B'Shabbato. Exactly. And that exactly does tie into that other
verse, exactly.
So... and so it also ties into... into... into... ראש חודש. Rosh
Chodesh. I'm sorry... דוד David was also tied into...
Right, exactly. Exactly. So, פשט Pshat in the פסוקים Psukim definitely is
that there was, like you know, for us, ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh
doesn't mean anything. It means חצי הלל Chatzi Hallel and מוסף, Musaf,
right? But it does mean that ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh was... bringing
a מוסף Musaf did have some broader resonance and significance of a
חג. But again, this is being read not as ראש חודש Rosh
Chodesh but as ראש השנה. Rosh Hashanah תנו רבנן: Tanu Rabbanan: כי
חוק לישראל הוא משפט לאלקי יעקב. Ki Chok L'Yisrael Hu Mishpat L'Elohei
Yaakov. מלמד שאין בית דין של מעלה נכנסים לדין אלא אם כן
קידשו בית דין של מטה את החודש. Melamed she'ein Beit Din Shel
Ma'alah nichnasim ladin ela im ken kidshu Beit Din Shel Matah et
hachodesh. So
this is a beautiful idea. You know, it's a common idea in
general תורה שבעל פה Torah SheBa'al Peh is the partnership between God
and the people. God gives the law, we interpret it and apply
it, so we're sort of partnering with God in what the תורה
Torah is. We also partner with God in terms of the calendar,
right? That there's on the one hand the natural idea of שבת
Shabbat which just occurs all by itself. But then you get to
the מועדים Moadim and אשר תקראו אותם. asher tikre'u otam. On the
one hand, sort of God creates the natural reality of the moon,
but we still have to look at it, interpret it, you know,
and give it religious significance. So there's like a type of תורה
שבכתב, Torah SheBichtav, תורה שבעל פה Torah SheBa'al Peh going on there,
that type of partnership. And even in the very idea of this
being of ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah as a יום הדין, Yom HaDin,
which would seem like the whole idea of דין Din is you
as the sort of subject, you know, complete submission to authority, but
it's only through our role and participation and partnering that we create
it as a יום הדין, Yom HaDin, that we actually create... you
know, we sanctify the month and create the day as ראש חודש
Rosh Chodesh and hence as ראש השנה. Rosh Hashanah. So I think
a very powerful idea, particularly applied in general, but applied in the
context of דין. Din. Actually, it's a common theme I use sometimes,
common, whenever, when I have to give a sermon on ראש השנה.
Rosh Hashanah Thankfully I'm not a shul rabbi, so I don't have
to do it that often. But anyway, a good, a good sort
of... you know, in the ישיבה Yeshiva we talk about nuggets for
sermons. A good nugget that I have for a second day of
ראש השנה... Rosh Hashanah a second day ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah דרשה
Drasha is that, you know, there's the famous מדרש... Midrash... not famous,
whatever. Anyway, there's a מדרש Midrash or a, I think it's from
the זוהר, Zohar, a statement that the difference of the דין Din
on the first day ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah and the second day
ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah. is that the first day is like a
harsh דין, Din, and the second day is like a sweetened דין,
Din, a softer דין, Din, a more compassionate דין. Din. And what
I say is, you know, in one way that that's interpreted is
that the first day you're sort of judged on your own merits.
You know, who will stand before God on their own merits? The
second day, we're judged as a community and collectively, so you know,
there we have everybody else's merits and we're looked at as an
entirety and that's a sweet... that's a softer or sweeter דין. Din.
So what's the פשט? Pshat? So I say because if you think
about it, how can we call the second day ראש השנה Rosh
Hashanah a יום הדין? Yom HaDin? Right? Second day ראש השנה Rosh
Hashanah is just, it's like, it's because of ספיקא דיומא. Sfeika D'Yoma.
It's because of a מנהג, Minhag, it's because of a doubt. It's
like God never said it was a יום הדין. Yom HaDin. You
guys want to like not do מלאכה, Melacha, that's your business. Like
I only, I only said that the first day I was going
to judge you. So the חידוש Chidush is that, no, that we
can actually turn it into a יום הדין Yom HaDin by creating
it as a ראש השנה. Rosh Hashanah. We can also, in a
way, you know, work with God and make even make it what
God didn't say was a יום הדין, Yom HaDin, we're going to
make it as a יום הדין. Yom HaDin. But if what makes
it a יום הדין Yom HaDin is sort of us working, you
know, at the communal level to, you know, to change its status,
you know, so therefore it's a דין Din for us as an
entire community and for us sort of in terms of
our... as a people and our relationship with God and not just
as an individual. So that's my whole little second day ראש השנה
Rosh Hashanah דרשה. Drasha.
but goes to this idea of this גמרא, Gemara, underscoring, which is
true about every ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh and every מועד, Moed, but
underscoring the power of that idea in the context of יום הדין.
Yom HaDin. It's only יום הדין Yom HaDin because you've made, you've
been מקדש החודש. Mekadesh HaChodesh. Yeah.
So on הושענא רבה, Hoshana Rabba, at the very end of that,
we'd say sweeten the stricture.
Ah, right, right. Yeah, that idea of the sweetening up of the
דין. Din. Right. So that's מלמד שבית דין של מעלה נכנסים לדין,
Melamed SheBeis Din Shel Maala Nichnasim LaDin, the heavenly court does not
enter in, the court doesn't begin, the judge doesn't come in, the
witnesses don't come in, אלא אם כן קידשו בית דין של מטה
את החודש. Ela Im Kein Kidshu Beis Din Shel Mata Es HaChodesh.
You guys have to sanctify the month. Which again, if you didn't
sanctify the month, it'd still be ראש חודש Rosh Chodesh at least
by day 31, but you get the idea. תניא אידך, Tanya Idach,
we find another ברייתא, Baraita, כי חוק לישראל הוא. Ki Chok L'Yisrael
Hu. What does it mean חוק לישראל? Chok L'Yisrael? Right, so that
was חוק לישראל משפט לאלוהי יעקב. Chok L'Yisrael Mishpat L'Elohei Yaakov. The
Jewish people see it and make it a יום הדין Yom HaDin
and then it's a day of judgment. Here's another read of the
verse. אין לי אלא לישראל. Ein Li Ela L'Yisrael. Maybe it's only
a day of judgment for the Jewish people. אומות העולם מנין? Umos
HaOlam Minayin? How do I know for the other nations of the
world? תלמוד לומר משפט לאלוהי יעקב. Talmud Lomar Mishpat L'Elohei Yaakov. It's
a day of judgment for the God of Jacob, so it's the
God of Jacob, but still judgment is for everyone, not just judgment
for Israel. אם כן מה תלמוד לומר כי חוק לישראל? Im Kein
Ma Talmud Lomar Ki Chok L'Yisrael? So why does it say start
by saying a judgment, a law, an edict for Israel? מלמד שישראל
נכנסים תחילה לדין Melamed SheYisrael Nichnasim Techila LaDin because the Israel, the
Jewish people are the ones that are judged first. כי ריש לקיש,
Ki Rish Lakish, like ריש לקיש Rish Lakish says, דאמר רב חסדא,
D'Amar Rav Chisda, like רב חסדא Rav Chisda says, דאמר רב חסדא
מלך וציבור מלך נכנס תחילה לדין. D'Amar Rav Chisda Melech Ve-Tzibur Melech
Nichnas Techila LaDin. If it's the king and the community all have
to stand in judgment before God, the king is the one that
gets judged first. שנאמר משפט עבדו ומשפט עמו. She-Ne'emar Mishpat Avdo U-Mishpat
Amo. God does the judgment of His servant, which is one individual,
so here understood to be the leader, ומשפט עמו u-mishpat amo and
then afterwards the judgment of the entire nation. So, מאי טעמא? Mai
Ta'ama? What's this, what is the reason behind this? I mean whatever
this means on a metaphysical plane, okay, but somehow there's a sense
of first focusing on the king and then the community or here
first Israel and then the rest of the world. So אי בעית
אימא לאו אורח ארעא למיקם מלכא אבראי. Ei Ba'is Eima Lav Orach
Ara LeMeikam Malka Abraei. Number one is, it's not דרך ארץ Derech
Eretz to have the king waiting and cooling his heels outside in
the hallway while all the other people are sitting in judgment. So
it's an issue of honor. The way you show honor to the
king, or honor to the Jewish people and so on, is they
get to go first. You get to go to the front of
the line. You don't have to wait in line. ואי בעית אימא,
Ve-Ei Ba'is Eima, I have no idea how to what that means.
I mean I know what it means but okay. ואי בעית אימא
מקמי דליפוש חרון אף. Ve-Ei Ba'is Eima Mikamei D'Leefosh Charon Af. No,
you want to be judged first before God gets very angry. He
starts seeing this sin and this sin and that sin. So by
the time he gets to the people he's judging later, then he's
fed up with all the sinning and then there's going to be
some more sort of consequence. Now okay, a high degree of anthropomorphism,
I can't even begin to explain what that means exactly, but I
would also sort of say that you could have said the exact
opposite, because this is being framed as, it's done this way in
order to let the king or by now the Israel off easier.
Right? And get the anger out at the people, that the anger
or get the anger out at the non-Jews. Okay, but in a
way if you think about the king analogy, the logic would go
the other way, right? The king is the one who has the
buck stops here, is the one who ultimately is responsible and if
the people are sinning or there's a problem, he's the one that
was in a position to do the most about it. So he's
the one that should actually be carrying the brunt of the weight
of responsibility. You could have said it that way. Why is he
judged first? Because not like God only starts looking at all the
sins after the other people, God knows the whole story and you
bring the person who's responsible, you bring them in first and you
give them the judgment for their responsibility, their heightened responsibility for everything.
And if you read it that way, the issue of the Jewish
people also, what's the idea of the analogy of king to people
and Jewish people to the rest of the world? You could speak
about this idea of, what's the פסוק pasuk say? It says רק
אתכם ידעתי מכל משפחות האדמה על כן אפקוד עליכם את כל עוונותיכם.
Rak Eschem Yadati Mikol Mishpachot HaAdama Al Kein Efkod Aleichem Es Kol
Avonoseichem.
We have this unique relationship to God. We should know
better in terms of what we do and our sinning and whatever.
We're supposed to be an אור לגויים. Or LaGoyim. So you could
speak about, you could make an analogy that way, we get judged
first because we have a larger responsibility and not in, so and
not the way the גמרא Gemara has it which is to get
off easier. Okay, so it's quite interesting sort of the way the
גמרא Gemara framed this and I have a hard, anyway I have
a hard time explaining exactly what the point is about the way
the גמרא Gemara sort of framed the whole issue. Yes.
Well the other problem is if the king isn't righteous, it has
to make God mad at the people even more.
Yeah, but that's the whole point here. God is going to get
mad eventually, so you'd rather be at the beginning of the line
rather than get the brunt of the anger. That's the whole point.
Again saying, okay, so I don't understand what that means that God
gets increasingly angry, like he only finds out about the stuff after
he's been through a few people. And also like it doesn't seem
to me like why should the king get off easy?
So...
For those who think that Wall Street titans got off easy, it's
consistent with that. Right, there you go.
But
you'll always find some patsy thesis to take the blame. All right.
ולישמיטין. U-lishmitin. Now, okay, so by the way, notice, I should note
that this was one read, probably not the most פשוטו pshuto of
this line in the משנה Mishnah that תשרי Tishrei? is ראש השנה
Rosh Hashanah. for being judged, right? It's one read the גמרא Gemara
has this nice little אגדתא aggadata so we have a nice little
discussion, but it's probably not פשט pshat in the משנה. Mishnah And
I want to remind you of this point that the first משנה
Mishnah which introduces the ראשי השנה, Roshei Hashanah, it's talking about obfuscating,
you know ראש חודש, Rosh Chodesh, sort of obfuscates the significance of
ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah, of תשרי, Tishrei. right? It's not any more
significant than אלול or than ניסן Nisan? or than whatever שבט, Shevat,
and you know, it's just somewhere buried in the list. And the
whole idea of it as a חג and as a יום הדין
yom hadin is also, you know, not really explicit, probably not even
פשט, pshat, probably not even פשט. pshat. So that's worth thinking about
again in a מסכת masechet I mentioned this on the first day
that's devoted to ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah. the way it starts by
downplaying, you know, and almost hiding the significance of ראש השנה. Rosh
Hashanah Okay, we'll get back to that once we start talking about
it as a יום הדין yom hadin more explicitly. Yes.
I read this phrase לפני חרון אף lifnei charon af exactly the
opposite way. Why can't it be that they go first because all
the anger comes out, right?
No, because of the word מקמי mikmei before, before
it increases the חרון אף. charon af.
I read it in מצמי matzmei pause, they come
first in order to absorb all the rage that comes out.
Yeah, it's a very creative way of reading but it's not פשט.
pshat. Okay. ולישמיטין. U-lishmitin. All right. ולישמיטין. U-lishmitin. So now, it's ראש
השנה Rosh Hashanah also for שמיטה. Shemitah. The שמיטה Shmita, year begins
on
תשרי. Tishrei Okay. מנלן? Menalan? How do you know? How do you
maybe? Who knows? Maybe it begins in ניסן? Nisan? How do you
know that the שמיטה, Shmita, you know, the seven year cycle is
incremented and defined by תשרי? Tishrei. דכתיב ובשנה השביעית שבת שבתון לה'
תהיה לארץ, De-chtiv u-vashanah ha-shvi'it shabbat shabbaton la-hashem tihyeh la-aretz, וליגמר שנה
שנה מתשרי. ve-ligmor shanah shanah mi-tishrei.
So it says a year and we learn from תשרי, Tishrei. דכתיב
מראשית השנה ועד אחרית שנה, de-chtiv me-reshit ha-shanah ve-ad acharit shanah, which
we just got through proving was תשרי. Tishrei. So if that שנה
shanah means תשרי, this שנה, shanah, this year cycle for the שמיטה
is also תשרי. וליגמר שנה שנה מניסן? Ve-ligmor shanah shanah mi-nisan? Why
not say שנה shanah also by ניסן? Nisan. דכתיב ראשון הוא לכם
לחודשי השנה. de-chtiv rishon hu lachem le-chodshei ha-shanah.
It's the first of the months which we know is ניסן. Nisan,
No, says the גמרא, Gemara דני שנה שאין עמה חודשים משנה שאין
עמה חודשים. dani shanah she-ein immah chodashim mi-shanah she-ein immah chodashim. The
two occurrences of ובשנה השביעית שנת שבתון תהיה לארץ, u-vashanah ha-shvi'it shnat
shabbaton tihyeh la-aretz,
you know ובשנה השביעית, u-vashanah ha-shvi'it, did not have the word חודש.
chodesh. And מראשית השנה me-reshit ha-shanah did not have the word חודש.
chodesh.
So that's simple שנה. shanah. Simple שנה shanah without the emphasis of
חודש chodesh is
תשרי. ואין דנין שנה שאין עמה חודשים משנה שיש עמה חודשים Ve-ein
danin shanah she-ein immah chodashim mi-shanah she-yesh immah chodashim from the verse
of ניסן, Nisan ראשון הוא לכם לחודשי השנה, rishon hu lachem le-chodshei
ha-shanah, which mentions שנה shanah in the context of חודש. chodesh. And
by the way, you know you could just say a technical point,
you know, different phrasing of the word so you know you have
to make your גזירה שווה gezerah shavah in the most similar way.
But it also could be that, no, the significance of ניסן Nisan
is the ראש השנה for חודשים. chodashim. The significance of ניסן Nisan
is that's when you begin the months, the month counting, but that
is not to be applied to other cases where it's about the
year as a whole. That starts at תשרי. So תשרי is, as
we said, there are two systems going on, the agricultural one, the
pre-מתן תורה mattan Torah one if you would, you know, that is
תשרי incremented, and then the ראשון הוא לכם, rishon hu lachem, the
ניסן one. And for these agricultural מצוות, we are going by the
agricultural cycle of the year which is defined as תשרי. Okay, so
that's שמיטה. וליובלות, U-leyovlot, and for יובל. Yovel So the גמרא says,
יובלות באחד בתשרי הוא? yovlot be-echad be-tishrei hu? Are יובלות does the
יובל Yovel? happen on the first of תשרי? יובלות בעשרה בתשרי הוא!
yovlot be-asarah be-tishrei hu! יובל Yovel happens on יום הכיפורים! Yom Kippur!
דכתיב ביום הכיפורים תעבירו שופר בכל ארצכם. de-chtiv be-yom ha-kippurim ta'aviru shofar
be-chol artzechem. So it's not the first of תשרי. And we know
in the משנה we deal with things that are in the middle
of the month separately, one in שבט, Shevat, 15 in שבט. Shevat.
So how here do we just say תשרי for יובל? Yovel It's
really the 10th of תשרי. The גמרא says, הא מני רבי ישמעאל
בנו של רבי יוחנן בן ברוקא היא. Ha manni rabbi yishmael beno
shel rabbi yochanan ben beroka hi. Yeah, you're right, but the author
of our משנה is רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Ishmael the son of רבי
יוחנן בן ברוקא Rabbi Yochanan ben Beroka that gives weight even for
יובל Yovel, to the first of תשרי. דתניא, De-tanya, it was taught
in a ברייתא, beraita, וקידשתם את שנת החמישים שנה, ve-kiddashtem et shnat
ha-chamishim shanah, you shall sanctify the 50th year. מה תלמוד לומר? Mah
talmud lomar? Why does it say sanctify the year?
לפי שכבר נאמר le-fi she-kevar ne'emar because since the verse says ביום
הכיפורים תעבירו שופר בכל ארצכם, be-yom ha-kippurim ta'aviru shofar be-chol artzechem, that
you blow the שופר shofar on יום הכיפורים, Yom Kippur, that's when
things start. יכול לא תהא מתקדשת אלא מיום הכיפורים ואילך, Yakhol lo
tehe mitkadeshet ela mi-yom ha-kippurim ve-eilach, maybe the year only gets sanctified
and gets its identity as a יובל Yovel year starting on יום
הכיפורים? Yom Kippur? תלמוד לומר וקידשתם את שנת החמישים. talmud lomar ve-kiddashtem
et shnat ha-chamishim. You sanctify the whole year, and when the year
begins, when the year begins is on
ראש השנה. מלמד שמתקדשת והולכת. Melamed she-mitkadeshet ve-holechet. The sanctity starts from
its very beginning, which as we learned before and we know from
שמיטה, which is part of the cycle, this is part of, is
תשרי. So the sanctifying of the year means the beginning of the
year. So now what is then the significance of יום כיפור? Yom
Kippur? So מכאן אמרו mikan amru רבי ישמעאל בנו של רבי יוחנן
בן ברוקא, Rabbi Ishmael bno shel Rabbi Yochanan ben Beroka, here is
how it would play out. מראש השנה עד יום הכיפורים, Me-Rosh Hashana
ad Yom HaKippurim, from ראש השנה to יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, לא
היו עבדים נפטרין לבתיהם, lo hayu avadim niftarin le-vateihem, the slaves would
not go home, ולא משתעבדין לאדוניהם, ve-lo mishtabdin le-adoneihem, they would not
be enslaved to their masters. You would be in this middle zone,
limbo. Right, limbo, exactly. The slaves would not go home, they would
not be freed. How do you know? Because what does the ספר
תורה sefer Torah say after you shall blow the שופר? shofar? Right.
העברת שופר בכל ארצכם. ha-avirat shofar be-chol artzechem. וקראתם דרור בארץ לכל
יושביה, ukratem dror ba-aretz le-chol yoshveha,
right, the פסוק pasuk from the Liberty Bell. You shall proclaim liberty
throughout the land. That is what the blowing of the שופר shofar
is. No bells, שופר. shofar. Okay, so the slaves are not free
until יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, but the year is sanctified from ראש
השנה. So the not yet this status as free men has not
yet been realized, but at the same time you cannot enslave them.
Okay, the same way you cannot work the land starting on ראש
השנה, right? Actually it was also true last year for the
שמיטה, but you cannot have that control over them, but that actual
ultimate redemption and freedom only comes on יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. לא
היו עבדים נפטרין לבתיהם, lo hayu avadim niftarin le-vateihem, they would not
go home, ולא משתעבדין לאדוניהם, ve-lo mishtabdin le-adoneihem, and they would not
be enslaved to their masters, אלא אוכלין ושותין ושמחין, ela ochlin ve-shotin
ve-smachin, they would eat and drink and rejoice,
anticipating what will happen, ועטרותיהם בראשיהם, ve-atroteihem be-rasheihem, they could be wearing
crowns on their heads, they could be going around acting like big
shots. כיון שהגיע יום הכיפורים, keivan she-higa Yom HaKippurim, and when יום
כיפור Yom Kippur came, תקעו בית דין בשופר, taku beit din ba-shofar,
they would blow the שופר. shofar. Then נפטרו עבדים לבתיהם, nifteru avadim
le-vateihem, then the ultimate redemption would occur, the slaves would go back
to their houses, ושדות חוזרות לבעליהם, ve-sadot chozrot le-vaaleihem, and the fields
would go back to their owners. What is also nice about this
is it also creates this, because this is all an image of
an עולם הבא Olam HaBa and a perfect world, and the יובל,
Yovel this sense of redemption does not happen automatically, there is a
middle period where things are, it is like things are better but
it is not yet, רב קוק, Rav Kook, it is אתחלתא דגאולה.
itchalta de-geula. It is not yet the ultimate redemption, okay? That takes
another stage already.
All right, so if the master can present the bill after יום
כיפור Yom Kippur for the food that they ate?
Yeah, I was
wondering who is paying for the food and drink? I was wondering
that. Okay, so the גמרא says like this. Okay, so therefore it
starts at ראש השנה. ורבנן, ve-rabanan,
and the rabbis, that by the way, nobody explicitly argues on רבי
יוחנן בן ברוקא, Rabbi Yochanan ben Beroka, at least not that we
see, but the גמרא assumes that that was just a single opinion
of the other... the rabbis would say it would all start on
יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. So
what do they do with the idea of sanctifying the fiftieth year
if it all starts on יום כיפור? Yom Kippur? That is to
tell you something else. שנים אתה מקדש, shanim ata mekadesh, you only
sanctify
years, וקדשתם את שנת החמישים שנה, ve-kidashtem et shnat hachamishim shana, you
only sanctify years, אי אתה מקדש חדשים, i ata mekadesh chadashim, you
do not sanctify months. What does that mean? Because there actually is
an opinion which the גמרא is now attributing to these rabbis that
says that in a normal case of קידוש החודש kiddush hachodesh that
בית דין beit din does not have an obligation to do קידוש
החודש, kiddush hachodesh, that that happens naturally, but this act of מקודש
מקודש, mekudash mekudash, no, that role of sanctifying is limited to years,
the יובל Yovel year, it is not something you do by month.
Now that is very much against our assumption, right, we always hear
that בית דין beit din accepts the witnesses and does this act
of sanctification of מקודש. mekudash.
I do not think that they would say the act of...
I do not think so. Oh, you mean by יובל Yovel because
they were doing the מצווה, mitzvah, maybe. Okay.
So, as you say, the יובל Yovel and everything else, in reality
you can imagine it would be very awkward.
During these ten days? Oh yeah, maybe it is also to get
the masters acclimate them to what they are going to have to
do. It is very hard to do this, so if you have
ten days of building up to it.
Slow process or anything?
There you go. Moving on, okay. תניא אידך, Tanya idach, we learned
another ברייתא. braisa. יובל היא, Yovel hi, מה תלמוד לומר? ma talmud
lomar? It is the יובל year. What does that teach you? לפי
שנאמר lefi shenemar וקדשתם את שנת החמישים, ve-kidashtem et shnat hachamishim, sanctify
the fiftieth year. יכול כשם שמתקדשת והולכת מתחילתה, yachol keshem she-mitkadeshet ve-holechet
mi-techilatah, this is obviously reflecting רבי יוחנן בן ברוקא, Rabbi Yochanan ben
Beroka, if the sanctity begins and continues, starts at the beginning of
the year and then grows, so it starts on ראש השנה but
it ultimately reaches its apex on יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, so the
same way that is true at the beginning, כך מתקדשת והולכת בסופה,
kach mitkadeshet ve-holechet be-sofah, so
I would logically say maybe the same is true at the end,
like maybe it peters out at the end, like maybe from ראש
השנה of year fifty-one to יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, maybe there is
like a tapering off, the same way there was an acclimating... tapering-off,
if that is a word, there was an acclimating, there also might
be like a de-acclimatizing at the end. אל תתמה, Al tithama, do
not be
astounded, שהרי מוסיפין. she-harei mosifin. So maybe the תורה Torah would be
telling me that the יובל year should go through the יום כיפור
Yom Kippur of the next year. In the same way it moves,
there's a process of moving up, maybe there's a process of moving
down. תלמוד לומר, Talmud lomar, so that's why the verse says no.
יובל היא שנת החמישים שנה, Yovel hi shnat hachamishim shana, it is
the Jubilee year, the fiftieth year. שנת חמישים אתה מקדש, shnat hamishim
atah mikadesh, only the fiftieth year, ואי אתה מקדש שנת חמישים ואחת,
ve'ee atah mikadesh shnat hamishim ve'achat, you do not sanctify the fifty-first
year. And just one more line. ורבנן, Verabanan, now the Rabbis who
don't think there was an acclimating process, for them maybe it would
be obvious you would not go into the next year. So according
to the Rabbis, why do you need the פסוק pasuk to say
יובל היא? Yovel hi? Obviously it's only about the fiftieth year. For
the following purpose: to tell you שנת חמישים אתה מונה, shnat hamishim
atah moneh, you count the year, the fiftieth year,
and ואי אתה מונה שנת חמישים ואחת. ve'ee atah moneh shnat hamishim
ve'achat. Now you could read it as you don't count it as
fifty-one. And the answer is of course you don't count it as
fifty-one, it's fifty. So the ריהוטא rihuta of the גירסא girsa as
it says is without the ו. vav. You count this as the
fiftieth year and ואי אתה מונה שנת חמישים אחת. ve'ee atah moneh
shnat hamishim achat. You don't count the fiftieth year one. Why might
you count it as one?
One for the next cycle.
So here's the question: is it a forty-nine-year cycle or a fifty-year
cycle? When does one begin? Does one begin on year fifty or
on year fifty-one? So this is saying יובל היא שנת החמישים שנה,
Yovel hi shnat hachamishim shana, this is only year fifty, it is
not year one. Year one will be next year. Okay, לאפוקי מדרבי
יהודה, Le'apukei mi-Rabbi Yehuda, to reject the position of רבי יהודה, Rabbi
Yehuda, דאמר שנת חמישים עולה לכאן ולכאן, de'amar shnat hamishim oleh lecha'an
ulecha'an, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says year fifty counts as the fiftieth
year of the previous and the beginning, year number one, of the
next cycle. It's a forty-nine-year cycle. קמשמע לן דלא, Kama shma lan
d'la, and for them, they would read the פסוק to say it
is the fiftieth, all it is is the fiftieth year and that's
its entire identity. Year one will begin next year. Okay.